<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 * Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
 * contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
 * this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 * The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
 * (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
 * the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Commons SCXML Usecase - Stopwatch on Android</title>
  <author email="jakobsa@gmail.com">Jakob Sachse</author>
 </properties>

 <body>
 
  <section name="Purpose of this document">
   <p>This document wants to show a possible approach aimed at using 
      SCXML on <a href="http://code.google.com/android/">Google Android</a>.
	  That is why the focus lies rather 
      on the steps necessary for successfully deploying the statemachine than
      the application itself.</p>
     <subsection name="Stopwatch">
      <p>This usecase is based on the stopwatch example. If you should not be
      acquainted with the stopwatch usecase you would probably want to read this
      first. The modeling of the statemachine as well as the scxml markup 
      will not be covered here.</p>
     </subsection>
     <subsection name="Motivation">
      <ul>
       <li>Demonstrate steps to run a Commons SCXML Statemachine on Android.</li>
       <li>Demonstrate what dependencies are not covered by Android and how
           to cut those ties.</li>
      </ul>
     </subsection>
  </section>
  
  <section name="Android Background">
    <p>Android is a mobile operating system that is developed and released by the
    Open Handset Alliance. First handsets are expected to enter the market 
    by October '08. Android is based on Linux and runs a virtual machine called
    the Dalvik VM. The SDK provides tools for transferring java bytecode to dalvik
    compatible bytecode.
    </p>
    <p>Android comes with a subset of J2SE packages but also provides own libraries
    and other third party libraries. Interesting is the use of apache harmony as the
    implementation of its J2SE modules. 
    </p>
    <subsection name="Prerequisites for building the Android Application">
     <ul>
      <li>an installation of Android SDK 1.0 r1</li>
      <li>good to have: ADT Plugin for Eclipse installed</li>
      <li>knowing about the folder structure of an Android project.</li>
      <li>knowing about the Role of Activities in Android applications.</li>
      <li>understanding UI Layouts created by using Androids xml layout scheme.</li>
      <li>being aware of Services, Intents and ContentProviders is an advantage</li>
     </ul>
    </subsection>
  </section>
  
  <section name="Building the Android Application">
   <subsection name="The Stopwatch Logic">
    <p>As already mentioned this usecase is based on the stopwatch example. It uses 
    both the <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/commons/proper/scxml/trunk/src/test/java/org/apache/commons/scxml/env/stopwatch.xml">stopwatch.xml</a> 
    and the <a href="../xref-test/org/apache/commons/scxml/env/StopWatch.html">StopWatch.java</a>.</p>
   </subsection>
   <subsection name="The Stopwatch UI">
    <p>Here is the UI definition for the stopwatch: <a href="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/stopwatch_display.xml">stopwatch_display.xml</a>.
       Place it into /res/layout/ from the root of your project. Note how id's are declared and referenced. Declared
       id's will be available through the automatically generated R.java.
    </p>
   </subsection>
   <subsection name="The Stopwatch Activity">
    <p>Here is the Activity class <a href="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/StopWatchActivity.java.txt">StopWatchActivity.java</a> 
    which is the entry point of the application. That is also where the instance of StopWatch resides.
    Note how UI Elements are being referenced by using the R.java class. See also how a handler is used to display
    changes to the StopWatch from another Thread.
    </p>
   </subsection>
   <subsection name="Resources">
    <p>Commonly used strings are declared inside a <a href="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/strings.xml">strings.xml</a>
     in /res/values/. Once you put it there the R.java gets updated and you can reference the strings using that class.
    </p>
    <p>If you wish to have a non standard icon you can replace /res/drawable/icon.png with this icon.png: <a href="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/icon.png"><img src="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/icon.png"/></a>
    </p> 
   </subsection>
   <subsection name="Manifest">
    <p>Each Android application has a <a href="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/AndroidManifest.xml">AndroidManifest.xml</a>. It resides inside
    the root directory and is used to declare the overall structure of the application.
    </p> 
   </subsection>
  </section>
  
  <section name="Handling unmet dependencies">
   <p>The real challenge of running a commons.scxml statemachine on Android are it's dependencies. After adding all
   needed libraries to the build path build errors will still occur. The reason is that the dependencies are based on
   a standard J2SE. In contrast Android uses a subset of J2SE, meaning that several packages are missing. Dependencies to J2SE 
   are shown in this <a href="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/scxml-dependencies-on-android.png">UML Package Diagram</a>.
   Reviewing <a href="http://code.google.com/android/reference/packages.html">available packages on Android</a> results 
   in the conclusion that <code>java.beans</code>, <code>java.awt</code> and <code>javax.swing</code> are missing on Android. The dependency between Commons Beanutils 
   and <code>java.beans</code> is strong. For meeting this putting the <code>java.beans</code> module (<a href="http://harmony.apache.org/">Apache Harmony</a>) on the build path is a possibility. 
   That module in turn has a dependency to <code>harmony.kernel</code> that needs to be removed. The yellow color of some of the packages 
   in the diagram marks the places where code changes happened. These modifications removed the dependence to not available 
   yet disposable J2SE packages. For a better documentation take a look at the <a href="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/diff.txt">diff file</a>. 
   </p>
  </section>
  
  <section name="Building the .apk">
   <p>Building the application is a bit tricky as well. You will notice that ADT will break up with the following error:
   <code>"Conversion to Dalvik format failed with error 1"</code>. You will also find a detailed message that explains that
   you have tried to build a core library which is not recommended. To do so anyway you can pass <code>dx</code> (the java bytecode - dalvik bytecode transformer) 
   the <code>--core-library option</code>. Concluding that by core-library <code>java.*</code> packages where meant, and having in mind what is about to be added 
   there is no reason for giving up. The problem in passing the <code>--core-library</code> option is that there is no such possibility from within ADT. 
   That problem can be met by using the activityCreator tool (to be found inside the tools directory of the SDK). This tool will 
   create an empty project for you. This is meant for developers who are not using eclipse. Alongside with the project structure the 
   tool generates an ant build script. Putting that <code>build.xml</code> to the original eclipse project enables you to pass the <code>--core-library</code>
   option to <code>dx</code> when using <a href="http://ant.apache.org/">Apache Ant</a>.</p>
   <pre>
    &lt;target name="dex" depends="compile"&gt;
     &lt;echo&gt;Converting compiled files and external libraries into ${outdir}/${dex-file}...&lt;/echo&gt;
      &lt;apply executable="${dx}" failonerror="true" parallel="true"&gt;
      &lt;arg value="--dex" /&gt;
      &lt;arg value="--core-library" /&gt;
      &lt;arg value="--output=${intermediate-dex-ospath}" /&gt;
      &lt;arg path="${outdir-classes-ospath}" /&gt;
      &lt;fileset dir="${external-libs}" includes="*.jar"/&gt;
     &lt;/apply&gt;
    &lt;/target&gt;
   </pre>
   <p>Now its time to build and install the project on your emulator.</p>
  </section>
  
   <section name="The result">
    <p>
       <img src="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/android_1.jpg" style="width:191px;height:365px;"/><br/>
       (Figure 1: Begin in state "reset")<br/><br/>
       <img src="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/android_2.jpg" style="width:191px;height:365px;"/><br/>
       (Figure 2: Start puts the stopwatch in "running" state)<br/><br/>
       <img src="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/android_3.jpg" style="width:191px;height:365px;"/><br/>
       (Figure 3: Split causes the stopwatch to be "paused")<br/><br/>
       <img src="scxml-stopwatch-on-android/android_4.jpg" style="width:191px;height:365px;"/><br/>
       (Figure 4: The stopwatch in "stopped")<br/><br/>
    </p>
   </section>

 </body>

</document>
