<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
   Copyright 2003-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Commons SCXML</title>
  <author email="commons-dev@jakarta.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

 <section name="Commons SCXML">

  <p>
  The World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) Voice Browser Working Group recently
  announced the publication of the first 
  <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/scxml/">Working Draft of State 
  Chart XML (SCXML)</a>.
  SCXML provides a generic state-machine based execution environment based on Harel
  State Tables. SCXML is a candidate for the control language within 
  multiple markup languages coming out of the W3C (see Working Draft for details).
  <em>Commons SCXML</em> is an implementation aimed at creating
  and maintaining a Java SCXML engine capable of executing a state machine defined 
  using a SCXML document, while abstracting out the environment interfaces.
  </p>
  <p>
  The use cases for an SCXML engine are multiple and varied. Anything that can be
  represented as a UML state chart -- business process flows, view navigation bits,
  interaction or dialog management, and many more -- can leverage an SCXML engine
  library.
  </p>

  <subsection name="Status">
   <p>
    <ul>
     <li>This code is in the commons <i>sandbox</i></li>
     <li>The code is unreleased</li>
     <li>Methods and classes can and will appear and disappear without warning</li>
     <li>If you like the code and want to push it towards a release, join the mailing list!</li>
    </ul>   
   </p>
  </subsection>

 </section>


 <section name="Documentation">
  <p>
    <ul>
      <li>The latest <a href="apidocs/index.html">Javadoc</a>.</li>
      <li>The latest <a href="xref/index.html">source</a>.</li>
      <li>The <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/builds/jakarta-commons/nightly/commons-scxml">nightly build</a>.</li>
      <li>The <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/jakarta-commons/SCXML">wiki</a>.</li>
      <li>Commons SCXML <a href="usecases.html">usecases</a> (case studies).</li>
      <li>Assorted <a href="api-notes.html">API notes</a> (tutorials).</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
 </section>


 <section name="Releases">
  <p>
  This is a <i>sandbox</i> component, headed for a (first) 1.0 release.
  </p>
 </section>

 <section name="Support">
  <p>
   The <a href="mail-lists.html">commons mailing lists</a> act as the main support forum.
   The user list is suitable for most library usage queries.
   The dev list is intended for the development discussion.
   Please remember that the lists are shared between all commons components,
   so prefix your email by [SCXML].
  </p>
  <p>
   Issues may be reported via <a href="issue-tracking.html">ASF Bugzilla</a>.
   Please remember that Bugzilla is shared between all commons components,
   so prefix your issue by [SCXML].
  </p>
 </section>

 </body>

</document>
