<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 * Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
 * contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
 * this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 * The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
 * (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
 * the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Commons SCXML</title>
  <author email="dev@commons.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

 <section name="Commons SCXML">

  <p>
  <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/scxml/">State Chart XML (SCXML)</a> is currently a
  Working Draft published by the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C).
  SCXML provides a generic state-machine based execution environment based on Harel
  State Tables. SCXML is a candidate for the control language within 
  multiple markup languages coming out of the W3C (see Working Draft for details).
  <em>Commons SCXML</em> is an implementation aimed at creating
  and maintaining a Java SCXML engine capable of executing a state machine defined 
  using a SCXML document, while abstracting out the environment interfaces.
  </p>
  <p align="center">
  <img src="images/scxml-dev-cycle.png"
       alt="Development cycle when using Commons SCXML" />
  </p>
  <p>
  The use cases for an SCXML engine are multiple and varied. Anything that can be
  represented as a UML state chart -- business process flows, view navigation bits,
  interaction or dialog management, and many more -- can leverage an SCXML engine
  library.
  </p>

 </section>


 <section name="Documentation">
  <p>
  Latest documentation is available:
  </p>
  <p>
    <ul>
      <li>The latest <a href="apidocs/index.html">Javadoc</a>.</li>
      <li>The latest <a href="xref/index.html">source</a>.</li>
      <li>The <a href="http://people.apache.org/builds/commons/nightly/commons-scxml">nightly build</a>.</li>
      <li>The <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/jakarta-commons/SCXML">wiki</a>.</li>
      <li>Commons SCXML <a href="usecases.html">usecases</a> (case studies).</li>
      <li>A <a href="guide.html">user guide</a> containing assorted API notes and tutorials.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
  Documentation for the most recent release is also available via the left side
  menu bar.
  </p>
 </section>


 <section name="Releases">
  <p>
  The latest release is v0.6. Read
  <a href="http://svn.apache.org/viewvc/commons/proper/scxml/tags/SCXML_0_6/RELEASE-NOTES.txt?view=markup">v0.6
  release notes</a> before upgrading.
  <a href="http://commons.apache.org/downloads/download_scxml.cgi">Download v0.6!</a>
  </p>
  <p>
  The first release was v0.5. The initial release version number was chosen
  to be 0.5 (rather than a 1.0) to better convey the fact that the
  underlying W3C specification is still a Working Draft, and subsequent changes
  to the Draft may warrant changes to portions of the library API. The core
  Commons SCXML APIs (SCXMLDigester, SCXMLExecutor etc.) are stable.
  Portions such as processing of &lt;datamodel&gt; and &lt;invoke&gt; SCXML
  elements, on the other hand, are subject to change as further changes are
  expected in these sections of the W3C Working Draft. See Working Draft for
  details.
  </p>
 </section>

 <section name="Support">
  <p>
   The <a href="mail-lists.html">commons mailing lists</a> act as the main support forum.
   The user list is suitable for most library usage queries.
   The dev list is intended for the development discussion.
   Please remember that the lists are shared between all commons components,
   so prefix your email by [SCXML].
  </p>
  <p>
   Issues may be reported via <a href="issue-tracking.html">ASF JIRA</a>.
  </p>
 </section>

 <section name="Who is using it?">
  <p>
   Projects that use Commons SCXML:
   <ul>
    <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/taglibs/doc/rdc-doc/intro.html">Reusable Dialog Components (RDC)</a>,
        part of Apache Jakarta Taglibs - For choreographing the execution of speech components
        taking part in a voice interaction bounded by a RDC group container.</li>
    <li><a href="http://shale.apache.org/">Apache Shale</a> - For managing the flow of control in
        web based applications, using <a href="http://shale.apache.org/shale-dialog/">Shale dialogs</a>.</li>
   </ul>
  </p>
 </section>

 </body>

</document>
